Guide to the Hudson Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Hudson Family Papers
1885-1967
RG 253
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
This collection documents the work of Southern Presbyterian missionaries Waddy Hampton Hudson, his wife Maude Chapin Hudson, and their son George A. Hudson, primarily in Kashing, China (now Jiaxing, Zhejiang Province) from 1894 to 1940. Waddy Hudson was in charge of mission accounts, trained ministers, and preached in neighboring villages, traveling from Kashing in a house boat. George Hudson worked initially in Kashing and then in Taiwan following World War II, including a tent evangelism ministry.
Hudson, Waddy Hampton, 1867-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patricia Hankins, on behalf of Annie Chapin Hudson Hankins, 2013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Waddy Hampton Hudson was born in 1867 in Greenville, South Carolina. He graduated from Furman University in 1890 and from Princeton Theological Seminary in 1893. In December 1893, Hudson married Maude Chapin, who was born in Boston 1867. The Hudsons had seven children: George Alexander, David Venable, Eirenne Chapin, Lois Chapin, Maude Chapin, Waddy Hampton, and Annie Chapin.
Having been appointed missionaries under the Presbyterian Church, U.S., Waddy and Maude Hudson sailed for China on December 21, 1893, supported the Independent Presbyterian Church of Savannah, Georgia. They arrived in Sinchang, China in January 1894 and were engaged in language study until September 1895. With their fellow missionaries, the Hudsons established the Kashing Mission, which included missionary residences, a hospital, a church, and schools. Waddy Hudson remained in Kashing except for furloughs in the United States, until 1940, formally retiring in 1941. He died in 1960.
Waddy Hudson received honorary doctorates from Davidson College (1914) and Furman University (1922). His missionary duties included being in charge of the mission accounts, building churches, training ministers, and preaching in small towns in the Kashing area. He was the first Moderator of the Kashing Presbytery, engaged in famine relief work, and was a correspondent for the North China Daily News.
Maude Hudson supervised the hiring and training of teachers in the two schools she had established in Kashing, taught a Bible study class for women, ran the household, and cared for her seven children. The family traveled by houseboat to the outlying villages for religious work. Maude left China in 1918 due to ill health and died in 1934 in Warm Springs, Georgia.
George A. Hudson, the eldest son, was born in China in 1894 and lived there, educated by his mother, until he was 16. After one year of high school in Davidson, North Carolina, he attended Davidson College for three years before transferring to the University of South Carolina and graduating in 1918 with B.A. and M.A. degrees. He received a B.D. degree from Columbia Seminary in Columbia, South Carolina and later received Th.M. and Th.D. degrees from Union Seminary, Richmond, Virginia. Hudson returned to China after graduating from seminary, also supported by the Independent Presbyterian Church of Savannah, Georgia. Following the Communist takeover in China, Hudson worked in Taiwan, primarily in tent evangelism and church extension. He conducted 129 evangelism campaigns in frontier villages and helped to organize and build more than 50 churches and chapels following the tent campaigns. Hudson retired in 1966 and died in 1982.
Scope and Contents
The Hudson Family Papers document the work of two generations of Southern Presbyterian missionaries in China and Taiwan. Letters from Waddy and Maude Hudson to his family in the U.S. provide detailed descriptions of their surroundings and mission work. The correspondence documents primarily the earlier years of the Hudsons' work in China, before 1918. There is little correspondence of the Hudson children, but George's mission work in Taiwan (Formosa) is documented by clippings and photographs. Also of interest in this collection are reports of Southern Presbyterian mission stations, hospitals, and schools in China as well as photographs of the Hudsons' evangelistic boat and tent ministries. Additional documentation of Waddy Hudson's work is available in the archives of the Independent Presbyterian Church of Savannah, Georgia held at Emory University.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Collected Material
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
V. Photographs
Missions -- China; Hudson, Waddy Hampton, 1867-1960; Hudson, George Alexander, 1894-1982
- Correspondence, 1885-1960; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Waddy to parents
      - Observations about life away from home; enters Princeton Theological Seminary (1890); interest in missions, 1885 Mar - 1891 Apr (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - At seminary, re. preaching, personal relationships, 1892 Jan - Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Goes to Devil's Lake, North Dakota to work in a church for the summer, 1892 May - Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Finishes summer ministry, reports to Princeton; brother William also attending Princeton; attends American Inter-Seminary Missionary Alliance meeting in November, 1892 Jul - Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Preparing to apply for missionary work under Southern Presbyterian church; graduates from Princeton in May; goes to Savannah to preach, 1893 Feb - Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Waddy and Maude to parents
      - Waddy Hudson and Maude Chapin married on December 5, 1893; traveling west, sail for China on December 21, 1893 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Enroute to China; arrive in Shanghai; language study, 1894 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Based in Sinchang for language study;daily life; move to Hangchow for summer, birth of son George on October 1, 1894 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - WHH preaching in Chinese, descriptions of Chinese homes and lifestyle; procurement of property in Kaishing [Kashing, Jiaxing] for new station with Dr. Venable, 1895 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - WHH and Dr. Venable establishing medical and evangelistic work in Kashing; to Hangchow for summer; births of children David and Lois, 1896 Jan - 1901 Jun (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - In Mokanshan for summer; property procured for school in 1906; WHH director of Seminary; boat ministry attacked by robbers; unrest in Kashing, 1904 Aug-1908 Jan (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - On furlough in U.S. during 1911; resumes ministry in Kashing, 1911 Jul-1918 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Maude to Waddy
      - Dated letter expresses concern for Waddy traveling, 1894 Dec, no dates (Box 1)
    - Waddy to/from siblings
      - Wilton: regarding business at home, regarding family in China, 1908-1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Lois: including regarding her marriage, 1894-1906 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Austin: regarding business at home, family, gifts to Hudson Memorial, 1894-1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General correspondence
    - Circular letters to "Dear Home Folks" from Hudsons, 1923 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters of Hudsons to/from S.M. Alexander, Chu Nien-ku, H.G. Hallock, E.M. Lippin, K.K. Keh, Frank Price, W. Stuart, Walker, Young, 1892-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters of others, including WHH's father to his wife, other family member correspondence, 1893-1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings, 1905-1957, 1997; Series II
  - By Waddy
    - "The Kashing Story" (A report to the Independent Presbyterian Church of Savannah, Georgia, 1957); "Gods and Demons" (published in Chinese Recorder, 1920); "Impressions from U.S.A."(n.d.); "Back in China" (1918), "The Next Leaders" (n.d.); "The Outlook for Christianity in China"; newspaper articles, miscellaneous notes, 1918-1957, no date (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - By Maude
    - Description of their home and surroundings in China, no date (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - By Lois
    - Miscellaneous writings and poems, primarily from her school days, 1905-1920 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - By George
    - "A Five Point Program for the Far East" (n.d.); "Walking in Darkness" (n.d.); "Communism in China and its Challenge" (1951)' "Tent Evangelism in Formosa" (1952), 1951-1952, no date (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - By others
    - Memoir of Henrietta McCaslin Hutcheson Schwartz for years 1910-1932, daughter of Strause and Allen Hutcheson, missionaries in Kashing, Chekiang [Jiaxing,Zhejiang], 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Collected Material, 1901-1946; Series III
  - Related to Presbyterian Church, U.S missions, including reports, notes regarding mission property in China, 1931-1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Including biographical information on missionaries Wade Hampton Venable, Hampden DuBose, John Leighton Stuart; agreement for sale of boat "Lucy Roy", 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Regarding Sutsien Station, Hangchow Station, Suchowfu Station, Hwaianfu Station, 1926-1936, no date (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Regarding Kashing Station, including property records, 1932-1942, no date (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Tsingkiangpu General Hospital annual reports, 1930, 1934, 1938, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Elizabeth Blake Hospital, Soochow - brochures, annual reports, 1921, 1924, 1931, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sutsien General Hospital, Goldsby King Memorial Hospital (Chinkiang), Kashing Christian Hospital, photos of Southern Presbyterian medical missionaries in China, 1923-1939, no date (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Brochures regarding Southern Presbyterian medical work in China, 1929, no date (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Brochures and documents relating to schools, including Kashing High School, Kiangyin schools, Union Bible School, Hangchow Christian College, Bible Teachers Training School for Women, 1915-1946 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Booklets, including related to missionary education, and "Rev. Hampden C. DuBose, D.D. and the Anti-Opium Movement in China" by Plamer C. DuBose, 1925-1944, no date (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Booklets relating to missionary education and Southern Presbyterian missions in China, 1915-1944, no date (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Booklets relating to missionary education and missions, 1918-1944, no date (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chinese language materials, including manuscript "confession of faith" (1901). Lord's Prayer in Sinchang dialect, "Thirty Lessons in the Life of Jesus Christ" (published by China Baptist Publication Society, 1937), illustrated "reader", 1901-1937, no date (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper clippings, primarily related to China and mission work (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Photocopies of articles from "The Bi-Monthly Bulletin", including regarding robber attack on Rev. W.H. Hudson, activities of Kashing mission station, no date (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Kashing High School yearbook, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Hillcrest School yearbook, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Book: "Our China investment: sixty years of the Southern Presbyterian Church in China" by P. Frank Price, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1890-1967, n.d.; Series IV
  - Fabric banner with embroidered Chinese characters (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Waddy Hampton Hudson: biographical and genealogical information, including "This Is Your Life" memoir, obituary (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - WHH recommendations and certificates for college and seminary, appointment as missionary, honorary degree from Davidson College, 1890-1929 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - WHH passport, wedding announcement, biographical clippings and documents, cards, 1893-1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - WHH personal financial records, 1902-1957 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - George A. Hudson: biographical information, including resolution from Decatur Presbyterian Church with biographical sketch, 1918-1967 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - GAH: biographical information: newspaper and magazine clippings (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Photographs, 1894-1950s; Series V
  - Family portraits and group portraits, family bungalow at Mokanshan (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Portraits and group portraits: missionary colleagues, Chinese colleagues, school groups (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Portraits and group portraits: Chinese individuals, including school groups (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Group portraits: Chinese and Western individuals (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Group portraits: Chinese and Western individual (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Buildings and scenery in China (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Boat ministry (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Tent evangelism ministry of George A. Hudson (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Tent evangelism ministry of George A. Hudson (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous individuals and scenes (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Album: Family, friends, scenery (Box 5, Folder 60)